<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Infofiche</title><link>https://infofiche.uk/</link><description>SFF, linguistics and related and unrelated</description><atom:link href="https://infofiche.uk/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:seventeenmagpie@infofiche.uk"&gt;Seventeen Magpie&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 20:42:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>When the languages might not be fictional, or Too Like The Lightning</title><link>https://infofiche.uk/posts/when-the-languages-might-not-be-fictional-terra-ignota/</link><dc:creator>Seventeen Magpie</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Too Like the Lightning&lt;/em&gt; by Ada Palmer is the finest book of fiction I've read this year and one of the weirdest and most alienating SF experiences I've ever had. Along with its explorations of gender, philosophy, religion and (dys/u)topian ideas are implied explorations of language, which is what I'm going to deal with today. I have only read book one of the series so this post is partially speculative and I look forward to returning with another once I have finished the rest. I've divided this into 2 parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The state of language in the twenty-fifth century (Worldbuilding),&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Invisible multilingualism (Textual),&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which I'll start with 'neath the fold...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://infofiche.uk/posts/when-the-languages-might-not-be-fictional-terra-ignota/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>sf</category><category>sf-linguistics</category><category>terra-ignota</category><guid>https://infofiche.uk/posts/when-the-languages-might-not-be-fictional-terra-ignota/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 05:05:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Language, Alienation and Assimilation in Arkady Martine's *A Memory Called Empire*</title><link>https://infofiche.uk/posts/language-alienation-and-assimilation-in-a-memory/</link><dc:creator>Seventeen Magpie</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Meta note: new posts are on the nth day of the nth month at the nth minute, nth hour, nth second. Be there or be square (I am the square when I forget to post.) Also, I've added comments since you last saw me. Please use them responsiby.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello readers! Wellcome to the second SFF linguistics blog post, this time about alienation and assimilation in &lt;em&gt;A Memory Called Empire&lt;/em&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Memory Called Empire&lt;/em&gt; (Arkady Martine, 2019) is a political thriller space opera. It is also a powerful story about assimilation and alienation in relation to an alluring and hostile culture. Martine does this by endearing us with the viewpoint protaganist, Mahit, and skilfully showing the forces of alienation and assimilation she experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the (many) tools Martine uses to achieve this is language. Mahit does not speak the language of the Empire, Teixcalaan, (the empire and the language share the name) natively; She learnt it with care and dedication and each of her encounters with it is also an encounter with the alien, which she shares with the reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://infofiche.uk/posts/language-alienation-and-assimilation-in-a-memory/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (8 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>a-memory-called-empire</category><category>sf</category><category>sff-linguistics</category><guid>https://infofiche.uk/posts/language-alienation-and-assimilation-in-a-memory/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 03:03:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Infofiche Update</title><link>https://infofiche.uk/posts/infofiche-update/</link><dc:creator>Seventeen Magpie</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello! I'm Seventeen Magpie and I'm taking this post to outline my plans for the coming year and establish some things. It's mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, this is actually the second post. I've already put out a discussion of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://infofiche.uk/posts/alien-language-in-barrier-by-vaughan-and-martin/"&gt;language barriers in *Barrier*&lt;/a&gt; so you can read that already. That is the kind of thing this blog is concerned with - SFF and linguistics and how they are used to tell stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I've started a list of 'has reads'. It's available on the sidebar. I'm deliberately not reviewing every book on there because I won't enjoy doing that. The list is mostly for my own interest to see what I read, when, how much &amp;amp;c. but I expect it will be useful if you're wondering - ever - 'has Seventeen Magpie read X?' and it can save you asking me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, I have a tenuous plan for what posts you have coming up (not in this order):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How fictional languages are used in &lt;em&gt;A Memory Called Empire&lt;/em&gt; to explore assimilation and alienation,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neopronouns in &lt;em&gt;A Half Built Garden&lt;/em&gt; (when that book comes out),&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The start of a theory series where I outline my approach to fictional language based criticism and establish key terms,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A love letter to &lt;em&gt;Outer Wilds&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, timing. I'm going to aim for a post a month, so you've had your post for February and the next one - probably from that list but I haven't decided which - will come around the start of March.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I look forward to seeing you then! Take care.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>infofiche</category><guid>https://infofiche.uk/posts/infofiche-update/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Language Barriers and Aliens in Barrier</title><link>https://infofiche.uk/posts/alien-language-in-barrier-by-vaughan-and-martin/</link><dc:creator>Seventeen Magpie</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A rancher and an illegal immigrant find themelves stranded on an alien spacecraft, their own language barriers dwarfed by that they have with their captors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barrier is a comic by Brian K. Vaughan and Marcos Martin, with Muntsa Vicente. It is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://panelsyndicate.com/comics/barrier"&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt; (pay what you want!) and its well worth a read for when my descriptions are sub-par. The thing that caught my eye, aside from it being an "unconventional drama about violence, language and illegal immigration," was the fact its a Spanish/English bilingual comic, and since I can read Spanish, I decided to give it a go. Spoilers beyond!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://infofiche.uk/posts/alien-language-in-barrier-by-vaughan-and-martin/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>comics</category><category>language-barriers</category><category>review</category><category>sf</category><category>sff-linguistics</category><guid>https://infofiche.uk/posts/alien-language-in-barrier-by-vaughan-and-martin/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What's in a name?</title><link>https://infofiche.uk/posts/whats-in-a-name/</link><dc:creator>Seventeen Magpie</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;poke&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seventeen Magpie. A significant number and noun. Going with the theme of the blog, until I come up with a better pseudonym.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://infofiche.uk/posts/whats-in-a-name/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>infofiche</category><guid>https://infofiche.uk/posts/whats-in-a-name/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 16:55:44 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>